Luz Marina Rodriguez Papers, 1945-2006
Sophia Smith Collection
Luz Rodriguez papers
1945-2006
1968-2006
Rodriguez, Luz
539
10 boxes (8.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Reproductive rights advocate. Papers include organization, conference, and symposia materials; appointment books; writings; educational records; correspondence; photographs; and memorabilia. They document Rodriguez's many professional activities, especially her activism in health and education for women of color, including SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective and the Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights. In addition they document her activities on behalf of Hispanics in New York City such as Baile Boricua Dance Company, Charas, and Dominican Womens' Development Center; as well as other neighborhood, educational, family-oriented, and health-related organizations and initiatives. There are also family materials, New York University course work and student papers, early correspondence, speeches, and writings.
Luz Marina Rodriguez was born in New York City on March 7, 1956, and grew up on the Lower East Side. She was the eldest of three children of Elsa Rodriguez Vazquez and Luis Rodriguez Nieto, Sr., who had both recently emigrated from Puerto Rico as part of Operation Bootstrap, a government economic investment into the Puerto Rican economy. Her father held a variety of jobs, including electronics repair and night security work, while her mother sold Avon products.
After graduating from Seward Park High School in 1974, Rodriguez spent two years immersed in social and cultural activities in her Puerto Rican neighborhood, which became known as Loisaida (a Latino pronunciation of the Lower East Side). She was deeply involved in The Real Great Society, a gang outreach and community empowerment organization created in 1964 to engage youth in addressing local needs, especially sweat equity projects to create affordable housing. She was also an active participant in Charas/El Bohio, a cultural center where she taught Puerto Rican folkloric dance.
After studying dance at Pratt Institute, Rodriguez graduated from New York University as a dance therapy major in 1982. College research into the sterilization of, and birth control experimentation on, Puerto Rican women planted the seed of later reproductive rights activism.
Rodriguez defines herself as a servant-leader. She has continued to combine grassroots social justice work with administrative leadership in non-profit organizations, including Henry Street Settlement, East Side Family Resource Center, Dominican Women's Development Center, and Casa Atabex. In 1996 she became Executive Director of the Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights and played a critical role in the formation of the SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective. In 2011, she become co-chair of the Management Circle of that organization. A specialist in organizational development and non-profit sustainability, Rodriguez currently serves as bilingual training coordinator at the New York City headquarters of the Foundation Center.
In 1994 in recognition for her advocacy work, Rodriguez was awarded a Windcall Residency, a retreat program for those who work for social justice. She is a published poet, playwright, aspiring sculptor, and she remains active in SisterSong. She was married to Norbeto Cruz and later divorced. She has two sons, Gabriel and Abran-Lumi, a step-son, a foster daughter, a kinship foster child, and four grandchildren.
The Luz Marina Rodriguez Papers contain 8.5 linear feet of organization, conference, and symposia materials; appointment books; writings; educational records; correspondence; photographs; and memorabilia. The papers are particularly strong in documenting her many professional activities, especially her activism in health and education for women of color, including SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective and the Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights. In addition they document her activities on behalf of Hispanics in New York City such as Baile Boricua Dance Company, Charas, and Dominican Womens' Development Center; as well as other neighborhood, educational, family-oriented, and health-related organizations and initiatives. There are also family materials, New York University course work and student papers, early correspondence, speeches, and writings.
This collection is organized into seven series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1974-2003)
II. CORRESPONDENCE (1968-1970)
III. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS (1986-97)
IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES (1973-06)
V. SUBJECT FILES (1974-1998)
VI. PHOTOGRAPHS AND MEMORABILIA (1945-2005)
VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS (1997-1999)
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions. Original audio-visual materials are closed to research.
Periodic additions to this collection are expected.
Luz Marina Rodriguez began donating her Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2006. Periodic additions to this collection are expected.
Rodriguez, Luz; Ross, Loretta J.; Hispanic American women -- Biography -- Sources; Hispanic American women -- Medical care; Latina women -- Social conditions -- History; Puerto Ricans -- United States -- Social conditions; Reproductive health -- United States -- History -- Sources; Reproductive rights -- United States -- History -- Sources; Women -- Health and hygiene -- United States -- Sources; SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective (Atlanta, GA); Latina Roundtable of Health and Reproductive Rights
Additional material on Luz Rodriqeuz can be found in her interview for the Sophia Smith Collection's Voices of Feminism Oral History Project and SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1974-2003, 2 linear ft.
  This series is arranged alphabetically and contains address books; calendars; day planners; family material related to her foster child, Tanya Vasquez, and sons Gabriel and Abran; financial material related to two court cases, an accident claim, and medical bills. There are student papers, course work, grades, and financial information from New York University.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1968-1970, 1 linear inch
  This series is arranged chronologically and consists primarily of letters from childhood friends.
- SERIES III. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS 1986-97, 1.5 linear inches
  This series contains speeches, public testimony and writings. The writings are arranged alphabetically and consist of notes; a poem, "El Yunque"; a play, "Ghost Writer"; and an essay, "Seven Days to Life". There is a compact disc of Rodriguez reading her work in SERIES VII. AUDIO VISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1973-06, 2.25 linear ft.
  This series is arranged alphabetically and contains material related to more than twenty-one organizations in which Rodriguez was involved. The bulk of the series relates to Baile Boricua Dance Company, Charas, Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights, and SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective. The Baile Boricua Dance Company (a group devoted to folkloric dance of the Puerto Rican and Afro-Caribbean culture) contains articles and clippings, board of directors' materials, correspondence, notes, and performances. Charas (a grassroots community serving the Latina section of the New York Lower East Side) includes material about its founder Amando Perez, anniversaries, bylaws, El Bohio Community Center, financial materials, Loisada neighborhood materials, board of directors' meetings, programs, activities, and strategic plans. The Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights consists primarily of board of director and financial materials. The financial materials include information on a Ford Foundation grant received in collaboration with SisterSong and the resulting symposiums on reproductive health and women of color. SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective contains additional information on the Ford Foundation grant, meetings, national conferences, and miscellaneous programs. It also contains information on Moon Lodge and other collective members. Since Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights is part of the SisterSong collective, some materials overlap.
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES 1974-1998, .25 linear ft
  This series is arranged alphabetically and contains information on fourteen subjects. Of particular interest are materials on Hispanic art and a conference on women's alcohol and drug education.
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS AND MEMORABILIA 1945-2005, .75 linear ft.
  This series consists two subseries Photographs and Memorabilia. The Photographs subseries contains family and personal pictures, photographs of a 1998 SisterSong symposium, plus several unidentified photographs. Most of the photographs have been transferred onto two compact discs which are included in this series. The master compact disc is located in SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS. Memorabilia includes certificates, school items, and artifacts which include an address book and childhood diary, a book bag, buttons, business cards, name badges, and unidentified and miscellaneous items.
- SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS 1997-1999, 3 linear ft.
  This series is divided into two subseries: Use copies and Preservation Masters and originals. The Use copies subseries contains twenty-eight digital video discs and a compact disc of an interview with Rodriguez about the Foundation Center, information on the International Congress on AIDS in Manila, Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights Symposium, SisterSong, and Rodriguez reading from her work. Use copies are available for all the audio-visual materials. Preservation masters and originals are closed to research.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Address books, [see also SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS AND MEMORABILIA] (Box 1)
  - Biographical materials and resumes, 1993-2002, undated, [see also Job Search, 2002] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Calendars, day planners, and phone messages
    - 1992-97 (Box 1)
    - 1998-2003 (Box 2)
  - Family
    - Cruz, Gabriel [son], 1986-97, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Maldonado, Abran [son], 1981-98, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Vasquez, Tanya
      - New Jersey Department of Social Services, Department of Youth and Family Services: foster parents training
        - Foster care application, paperwork, references, printed material, and correspondence, 1985-95 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Foster Care Handbook, 1994-95 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Birth certificate and miscellaneous material, 1996-98, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Financial materials
    - Automobile accident claim, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Luz Rodriguez vs. the City of New York and Quality Taxi, Inc., Shellac Cab Corp., Milton Brachfeld and Morris Hirstart, 1979-81 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Medical bills, 1984-93, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Rali Apartments vs. Luz Rodriguez, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Interviews, [see SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS and Voices of Feminism Oral History project] (Box 2)
  - Job search, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Landmark Education,Self expression and leadership program, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New York University
    - Course work and student papers
      - Dance therapy
        - Student papers, 1978-80, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - Research material and miscellaneous, 1974-80, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Kinesiology, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Magazine and article writing, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Music therapy, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Psychological aspects of blindness, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Taino and Bomba research, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Women in the Urban Environment (paper on population control in Puerto Rico), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Miscellaneous, 1978-82, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Financial information, 1981-82, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Grades and transcripts, 1978-81, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Tisch School of the Arts, Musical Theatre Writing Program, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous, 1992-94, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
- SERIES II. CORRRESPONDENCE
  - Sympathy notes on death of her grandmother, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters and greeting cards, 1969-70, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
- SERIES III. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  - Speeches and public testimony, 1988, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Writings, [see also SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS - Luz Rodriguez reads from her work ]
    - "Directory of Women's Organizations" (with Monique La Rocque), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "El Yunque", undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Ghost Writer, A One Act Play," 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Seven Days to Life," 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- SERIES IV. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Baile Boricua Dance Company
    - Articles and clippings, 1973-82, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Board of Directors, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Notes, 1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Performances, 1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Canan Senior Center, 2002-03, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Charas
    - Amando Perez: articles and clippings, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Anniversaries, 1990, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Bylaws, 1974, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - El Bohio Community Center, 1999, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Financial materials, 1986-89 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Housing, 1973-87 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Loisaida, 1988-99, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Meetings
      - Board of Directors, 1989-90 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Miscellaneous, 1987-89 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - National Endowment for the Arts grant proposal, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Notes, 1999, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Programs and activities, 1988-90, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Strategic plan, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990-98, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Dominican Women's Development Center: English as a second language
    - Healthy heart
      - Curriculum, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Printed materials, 1991-95, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous, 1995, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Foundation Center
    - Amethyst Women's Project Conference, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Printed materials, 2003-06 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Weekly Reports, 2003-06 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Henry Street Settlement
    - Division of Youth Services: Beyond City Limits, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Youth Employment Program, 1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1994, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Innovations Board for Children and Family, 1991-92, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - International Congress on AIDS in Asia and the Pacific, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights, [see also SisterSong - Ford Foundation grant]
    - Board of Directors
      - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Development guidelines, retreat and workshop, 1994, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Meetings, 1995-98 (Box 4, Folder 8-19)
      - Miscellaneous, 1996, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Bylaws, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Financial materials
      - Fundraising
        - Flow charts, 1996-98 (Box 4, Folder 22)
        - Strategies, 1996-97 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Grants
        - Ford Foundation, [see also SisterSong]
          - Attachments for proposal, 1995-95 (Box 4, Folder 24)
          - Reproductive Health in Women of Color: An Exploratory Symposium I,New York, NY12-14 Oct. 1997 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
          - Reproductive Health in Women of Color: An Exploratory Symposium II, Savannah, GA28 Feb.- 3 Mar. 1998 (Box 4, Folder 27)
          - Follow-up 1998-99 (Box 4, Folder 27A)
        - New York Foundation, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 28)
        - New York Women's Foundation, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 29)
        - Public Welfare Foundation, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 30)
        - Roberts Woods Johnson Foundation, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 31)
        - Sister Fund, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Tax exempt forms, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Miscellaneous, 1998, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Little Sisters Project, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous, 1997-98 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Latino Commission on AIDS, 1997-98 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Learning Partners, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Lehman College Adult Learning Center (Counselor), 1993-94 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Little Mission Day Nursery
    - Board of Directors, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Employment issues and Executive Director evaluation, 2001-02 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Non Profit Finance Fund, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Personnel committee, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous, 2000-02, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - MANA of New York City, 1996-97, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - National School and Community Corps
    - Activities calendar, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 46-47)
    - Site Manager training, 1995-96 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Partnership Ministries, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Princeton Review Scholastic Aptitude Test tutor training, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - ProLibertad, 1994-97, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective, [see also SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS AND MEMORABILIA and SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS]
    - Ford Foundation Grant, [see also Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights]
      - Correspondence, budgets, proposals, and miscellaneous printed material, 1991-98 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Moon Lodge Women's Outreach, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Meetings and national conferences
      - Training I, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Exploring our Power, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Sexual Rights, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Past, Present and Future Eugenic Technologies and Ideologies, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Miscellaneous, 2003-04 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Voter education, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1985-2004 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Urban Rural Mission
    - Lifelines: Journey of Sex and Spirit, 2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Maquiladora Reader, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Washington Heights Ecumenical Food Pantry, 1994, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous organizations, 1983-2004, undated (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
- SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES
  - Agents (entertainers) lists, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Birth control, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Breast cancer, 1998, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Cervical cap, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Education and teaching, 1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Environmental organizations of New York, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Foundations, 1992-98, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Hispanic art
    - !AHA! Hispanic Arts News, 1990-95 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous, 1990-95, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Mexico, 1997, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Puerto Rico, 1987-97, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Women in business, 1992-95, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Women's Alcohol and Drug Education (Women's Action Alliance conference), 1989 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - United States Agency for International Development, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Yoga, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
- SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS AND MEMORABILIA
  - Photographs (original)
    - Family and personal
      - Luz Rodriguez and miscellaneous family, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Photographs from wallet, 1966, 1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Latina Roundtable on Health and Reproductive Rights, Reproductive Health in Women of Color Symposium II, Savannah, GA (70 colored snapshots and negative film strip)28 Feb.- 3 Mar. 1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Digital copies of above photographs (2 compact disc copies) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia
    - Address books and 5-year diary, 1968-75, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Certificates, 1945, 1962-2002 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Personal stationary, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - School material
      - Junior high school artifacts, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Junior and senior high school materials, 1963-72, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Miscellaneous, 1964-2005, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Simeon's art, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - "Star file" (constellations), undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Amethyst Women's Project bag,, notepad, paper clip, key chain/condom holder undated (Box 7)
    - Buttons (Box 7)
    - Napkin from junior high school prom night, "my first drink at Hawaii Kai" (Box 7)
    - Jousting tournament proclamation, undated (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1982-98, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
  - Use copies
    - Car - Hit and run accident, Nuyorican finals (1 DVD) 1999 (Box 8)
    - Foundation Center: interview with Luz Rodriguez (in Spanish) (1 CD)undated (Box 8)
    - International Congress on AIDS (4th) Manila, Philippines (1 DVD) 1997 (Box 8)
    - Latina Round Table on Health and Reproductive Rights Symposium (5 DVDs)March, 1998
      - #1 Introductions and Morning: Welcome & introductions from participants (Box 8)
      - #2 Project History and Future (morning session) & Sharing of our analysis; "Plotting our Garden (reports from small Workgroups) (Box 8)
      - #3 Dr. Virginia Floyd, Dir of Human Development & Reproductive Health/Ford Creativity & Structure for our Visions and Goals (Box 8)
      - #4 Creating a Vision Statement, Workgroup reports on 3-year projects Asian, Latina, African (Box 8)
      - #5 Continuation of Workgroup Reports African, Native American.. Discussion: Timeline/criteria for concept papers measurement tools (Box 8)
    - Luz Rodriguez reads from her work (1 DVD)undated (Box 8)
    - SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective (18 DVDs)
      - A. Love - Re-Cap on Day 1 - On racism (Box 8)
      - First training workshop for information on the project SisterSong, group for reproductive rights. Carmen Zorrilla, San Juan PR (2)March 1999 (Box 8)
      - Grants Administration 1, n.d. (Box 8)
      - Self -Help Intro, undated (Box 8)
      - Copies of microcassettes # 1-5 (10) (Box 8)
      - Human Rights 101-11, Loretta Ross, undated (Box 8)
      - RTI/SH Training, Dallas TX, Last day and farewells, undated (Box 8)
      - RTI 202 [tapes 1 and 2] (2) undated (Box 8)
  - Originals and master copies - CLOSED, see Box 8 for use copies
    - Car - Hit and run accident, Nuyorican finals (1 DVD and camcorder videocassette) 1999 (Box 9)
    - Family photographs digitized (1 compact disc)undated (Box 9)
    - Personal photographs digitized (1 original compact disc and compact disc master)undated (Box 9)
    - Foundation Center: interview with Luz Rodriguez (in Spanish) (2 compact discs)undated (Box 9)
    - International Congress on AIDS (4th) Manila, Philippines (1 DVD and 1 camcorder videocassette) 1997 (Box 9)
    - Latina Round Table on Health and Reproductive Rights Symposium ( 5 DVDs and 5 camcorder cassette tapes)March, 1998
      - #1 Introductions and Morning: Welcome & introductions from participants (Box 9)
      - #2 Project History and Future (morning session) & Sharing of our analysis; "Plotting our Garden (reports from small Workgroups) (Box 9)
      - #3 Dr. Virginia Floyd, Dir of Human Development & Reproductive Health/Ford Creativity & Structure for our Visions and Goals (Box 9)
      - #4 Creating a Vision Statement, Workgroup reports on 3-year projects Asian, Latina, African (Box 9)